A Guide to the Dr. Henry Thomas Skinner Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-ad
Dr. Henry Thomas Skinner Papers 1932-1984
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-ad
2716 items
Mrs. Skinner
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Dr. Henry Thomas Skinner Papers were given to the Library, without restrictions, by Mrs. Skinner of Hendersonville, North Carolina on May 6, 1987.
Biographical Sketch
This biographical information was taken from
Who's Who in America
, Vol. II, 1974-1975, 38th edition, p. 2851.
Scope and Content
The papers of the noted botanist and former director of the National Arboretum in Washington, D.C., Dr. Henry Thomas Skinner(1907-1984) of Hendersonville, North Carolina, consist of 2,716 items (10 Hollinger boxes, 3 linear feet), 1932-1984. This collection contains correspondence, printed material, articles, talks, photographs, newsclippings, and bound volumes, much of it pertaining to his life's work with ornamental plants (especially the azaleas native to North America), his memberships and activities in professional and horticultural organizations, and his directorship and continuing interest in the Morris Arboretum at the University of Pennsylvania, and the National Arboretum.
These are the personal files of Dr. Skinner, and do not contain any official files kept by him while an employee of the United States Department of Agriculture. Only a small quantity of his correspondence deals directly with his professional tenure at the Morris Arboretum or the National Arboretum. The majority of his letters are dated after his retirement in 1972 and include such general topics as: horticultural meetings, agendas, and programs; preservation of native flora and ecological systems; invitations to speak; requests for advice; awards given to Skinner; thank you's; requests to write government agencies in support of environmental issues; fundraising for various groups; plant identification, care, and propagation; and other plant-related topics.
Dr. Skinner conducted an extensive study and collection of wild species of azalea growing throughout the whole eastern part of the United States during the spring and summer of 1951. This resulted in his dissertation,
Character Patterns in the Early Flowering Azaleas of the Southern United States
(1952), written for the University of Pennsylvania. Other bound volumes in the collection pertaining to this research are two Southern collecting trip record books, an expense book, and a notebook regarding routes taken on the collecting trip. There are also two topical folders concerning native azaleas, one of which contains an article, "In Search of Native Azaleas," printed in the
Morris Arboretum Bulletin
in 1955.
A selective description of the contents and correspondents of the more important correspondence files is given below under each folder heading. For a complete list of all folder headings, consult the box listing at the end of this guide.
A: American Association of Botanical Gardens & Arboreta, Inc. and the location of papers for its history (1982 Oct. 31); Acacia Fraternity at Cornell; the University Botanical Gardens of Asheville, Inc.; Gregory Nace; invitation to do a talk for the Arthur Hoyt Scott Foundation(1980 Jan. 17); Jane Akers; Joseph Oppe; American Association of Nurserymen; Joe Adams; Historic Annapolis, Inc.; Mrs. Patrick Armsley; the Prince George Audubon Society; and "Arboreta -Some Thoughts on Their Significance and Possible Areas of Contribution" (1973 Feb. 20).
American Horticultural Society: seed program, the "new" AHS Azalea Handbook (1980 Jan. 4); symposiums; Donald Wyman and James Harlow, concerning the argument over the publication agreement concerning
The Peonies
(1961 & 1977-1978); Magnolia Checklist (1976 Jan. 5); Plant Science Data Center; and the "Bibliography of Cultivar Name Registration."
B: Bowman's Hill State Wildflower Preserve; Robert Barham; Janet Bowers Bothwell; Bowers Foundation; Alex Benisatto; Malcolm S. Barnes; Gordon A. Brandes( Filoli Center); Ray Brush
Hortus III
W. P. Bebbington& "Vascular Flora of Hitchcock Woods" (1976); Clarence F. Bent; Richard A. Brown; Hal Brace; "A Comment on Ivy," by Skinner (n.d.); Buildings of England Group; a gift of books to the Royal Horticultural Society Garden at Wisley; and biographical information on Clement Gray Bowers(1973 Jun. 6).
Boxwood Society: paragraph in honor of Edgar Anderson(1984 May 11); discussion of "Morris Dwarf" & "Morris Midget" (1981 Feb. 3); "Comments on Some of the Better Known Boxwood Varieties" by Skinner (1977 Sept. 29); boxwood registration form (1976 Jul. 3); "The Boxwoods of Birr Castle, Ireland" (1975 Sept. 14) and "Notes on Some Forms of Japanese Boxwood" (n.d.) both by Skinner.
C: list of former winners of the Norman Jay Coleman Award(1983 Oct.) and Skinner's recommendation that John Creech be given the award (1983 Dec. 20); Skinner's advice regarding the National Arboretum to Marc Cathey(1981 Jun. 12); William A.V. Cecil; and Dan Coleman.
Cornell Plantations: Ralph Curtis Memorial fundraising (1982-1984); "Inventory of Plant Materials" (1981 Aug. 11); Janet Bothwell(1980); and photograph of Cornell Class of 1936 (1976 Mar. 3).
D: James Deane, editor of
Living Wilderness
, regarding Martha Prince's manuscript about the Nantahala Forest controversy (1977 Apr. 7); and Francis DeVos.
E: Harold Epstein and the American Rock Garden Society talk (1975 Jan. 30).
F: Bill Flemer, III; Truman Fossum; Henry Fuller; William H. Frederick, Jr.; Lionel Fortescue; Rhododendron bakeri(1975 Jun. 3 & 17); "The Time Has Come," by Henry Fuller and other material about native azaleas (1974 Feb. 15, Mar. 25, & following).
G: Fred C. Galle; Kerume azaleas lists (1983); Garden Club of America
The Azalea Book
(1980 Nov. 25); Mrs. Johnson's watercolor paintings of native azaleas (1978 Nov. 9); Gulf Stream Nursery and Bob Talley; Gary Gerlach; Roger Grounds and liriopogons (1975 Jan. 30, Feb. 22, Mar. 3, and Apr. 14); Mary A. Gamble and boxwoods (1974 Oct. 26); and "The Edgar Anderson Balkan Boxwoods" by Gamble (1974 Jan.).
H: Polly Hill; Herb Society of America; Arthur W. Holweg; Horticultural Tour of Eastern United States (1977 Oct.); Edward W. Hughes; Frederic Heutte; Harold Hillier & Sons; Walter Hodge and
Hortus III
(1974 Jun. 18); E. D. Hirsch, Jr., concerning a test garden for rhododendrons at the University of Virginia(1973 Nov. 4); dwarf conifers and Humphrey Welch(1973 Apr. 10 & 19); the Holly Society of America and the registration of "Lydia Morris" (1973).
International Dendrology Society: newsletters, minutes, & etc.; and a photograph of an IDS tour group (1975).
I-J: Marion Jull; Marion Johnston; and Lady Bird Johnson(1966 May 22, & 1973 Feb. 28).
K: Austin C. Kennell; Frank P. Knight; August Kehr; Steven Kristoph; John S. Sheppard and the use of rhododendrons for erosion control (1976 Aug. 29); and Joseph Kettinger.
L: Kathleen Lahr; Clarence E. Lewis; Elizabeth Lawrence concerning the "Morris Dwarf" vs. "Morris Midget" (1980); Lynn Lowrey; George Lee's death (1978 Apr.); Skinner's review and comments concerning the Recommended Plant List printout (1973 Aug. 15, & 1978 Jan. 12); Ladew Topiary Gardens; Bob Lederer; P. S. Leathart with Skinner's list of "Notable Exotics Grown in the United States" (1976 Apr. 5); Marion Flook regarding phloxes; Dick Lighty; the distribution of native azaleas (1975 Aug. 18); Skinner's Longwood Garden lecture; Adile Lovett; Richard M. Lewis; and Plant Questionnaire criticisms (1974 Jan. 3).
M: Betty Miller; Philip R. Milroy regarding the preservation of plants on the old "Meadows" estate of Fletcher, North Carolina(1982 May 10 & Jun. 3); Kenneth Knox; Champion Big Trees of North Carolina (1982 Jan.); Alfred S. Martin; Brian Mulligan; Skip March; Loy Marks; J.C. McDaniel regarding a Checklist of Cultivated Magnolias (1976 Jan. 5 & 15); book donations to Wisley Gardens(1974); International Dendrology Society tours; controversy over restuarants at the Hiram M. Chittenden Locks Garden(1973).
Morris Arboretum: Paul W. Meyer; Plan for the Development of the Morris Arboretum; Fact sheet; J. J. Willaman; native azaleas; George L. McNew; and Gordon A. Brandes.
N: North Carolina Botanical Garden; Northwest Ornamental Horticultural Society, Inc.; Dr. Frederick G. Meyer; and National Council of State Garden Clubs.
National Arboretum: Rhododendron japonicum(1984 May 9 & 16); Theodore R. Dudley; special plant distribution lists; seed lists; photograph of National Arboretum Advisory Council Meeting (1979 Jun. 14); and Skinner's comments regarding Dudley's Biota of North America Committee Rhododendron Listing (1978 Dec. 8).
O: Joseph W. Oppe; Rhododendron japonicum(1984 Jul. 29); Michael MacCaskey; and Ortho Books, Chevron Chemical Company.
P: Martha Prince; Ben Parry; Pacific Tropical Botanical Garden; Mateo Lettunich; J.B. Paton; Martha Prince's "To Save A Mountain" (1977 Oct. 1); the Nantahala National Forest clear cutting controversy (1976-1977); and the Pennsylvania Horticultural Society.
R: Royal Society of Arts; the American Rhododendron Society; the American Rock Garden Society; the Republican National Committee; Martha K. Roane; and Allan H. Reid.
Royal Horticultural Society: John Cowell; plant name changes such as Rhododendron japonicum(1984 Sept. 6); Suzanne Lucas; Frances Perry; Veitch Memorial Medal(1983 Oct. 13); "The Royal Horticultural Society" by Suzanne Wolstenholme(1983 Mar.-Apr.); Chris Brickell; Chelsea Show; Lord Charles Aberconway; and John Hamer.
Rhododendron: Marshall Asher; Bill Tietjen and the seed exchange; Austin C. Kennell; William H. Gensel; Norton Booth; Dr. Donald Kellam, Jr.; and Phil Cofer.
S: Bess Shippy and her interest in ivies; Sutton Valence School; Stephen F. Smith; Harrison M. Symmes; Franklin Styer regarding the American Association of Nurserymen to Stabilize Nomenclature; Louise G. Smith; Brian Savage; Henri Schaepman concerning Shippy's book on ivies (1975); plant names and comments by Skinner (1974 Nov. 16); Russell Seibert; and J. R. Schramm.
T: Tryon Men's Garden Club; Pat and Tom Tinsley regarding landscaping his business (1977 Jan. 21); Time-Life Books
Shade Gardens
Bob Talley; Jacques L. Legendre Garden(1974 May 13); and Margaretta Taylor regarding the
Encyclopedia of Gardening
(1978 Jan. 28).
V: Charles Van Ravenswaay, director of Wintherthur; Skinner's comments regarding the Pine Checklist (1976 Aug. 9); Derk Visser; and the Winterthur Museum.
W: James Morton Smith; Winterthur Museum & Gardens; Gertrude and John Wister; Jim Wells; William Paca Garden(1980 May); Jim Harlow and
The Peonies
controversy (1978 Nov. 21); Conrad J. Wrzesinski; Anne Wood; W. G. Waters; Elfriede Walker; Robert Walpole; Helen H. Whiting; Williamsburg Garden Symposiums; Thomas Wheeldon; Donald Wyman; Joseph A. Witt; Humphrey J. Welch; and Whitemarsh Park conservation (1972 Dec. 1).
Y-Z: Wilbur H. Youngman; David N. Yerkes; and Isabel Zucker.
Dr. Skinner's second series of files are topical and only the contents and correspondents of a few will be described here. The following folders furnish additional insight into Skinner's career: Awards, Biographical Sketches, Photographs, Publicity, the Scrapbook File, and Social Functions.
The Azalea Handbook of the American Horticultural Society folder contains correspondence from Fred Galle, Frederic P. Lee, Harlan P. Kelsey, Wendell H. Camp, and David Leach. The file on the Nantahala National Forest includes correspondence from Martha Prince, S. I. Hayakawa, Herman E. Talmadge, and George McGovern; and discusses the Roadless Area Review and Evaluation and the Southern Highlands Coalition.
Skinner's article, "In Search of Native Azaleas," is found in the Native Azaleas folder, together with the correspondence of W. H. Camp, W. P. Lemmon, and S. D. Coleman.
Dr. Skinner was chiefly responsible for the production of the United States Department of Agriculture's Plant Hardiness Zone Map, and the same folder also contains "The Geographic Charting of Plant Climatic Adaptability" by Skinner.
His interest in rhododendrons is represented by several folders pertaining to that plant. A "Guide to Dexter Rhododendrons" is found in Rhododendron and Azalea Varieties; Rhododendron Japonicum contains correspondence from Dr. Edward Voss and R. K. Brummitt concerning the Botanical Code; and the
American Rhododendron Society Quarterly Bulletin
contains Martha Roane's article "The Species of Rhododendron Native to North America," with letters also from Edward C. Egan, Jim Wells, and King & Paton of Scotland.
Donald Voss, Edwin K. Parker, and Paul W. Meyer write concerning Rhododendron Registration, while Judy Young and Karen S. Gunderson correspond regarding the Rhododendron Species Foundation.
Dr. Skinner's Scrapbook File includes the following: Alfred S. Martin, Jack Brooks, Earl L. Butz, Karl Loevenich, John Mack Carter, Frederick P. Lee, John C. Wister, H. F. Du Pont, Ezra Taft Benson, Fred J. Chittenden, and Anthony Montague Rowe for Sir Winston Churchill.
The bound volumes of this collection include those connected with Skinner's native azalea collecting trip in 1951, several notebooks concerning rhododendrons and azaleas, and his thesis and dissertation.
Organization
Dr. Skinner's original folder arrangement, in reverse chronological order, and headings have been maintained as much as possible. The collection is organized into three series: 1) correspondence files; 2) topical files; and 3) bound volumes.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - "A", 1973-1984 (Box Box 1)
  - American Horticultural Society, 1961-1982 (Box Box 1)
  - "B", 1963, 1971-1983, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Boxwood Society, 1962-1984, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - "C", 1973-1983 (Box Box 1)
  - Camellia, 1973-1981 (Box Box 1)
  - Cornell Plantations, 1973-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - "D", 1973-1983 (Box Box 2)
  - "E", 1973-1977 (Box Box 2)
  - "F", 1972-1984 (Box Box 2)
  - "G", 1974-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - "H", 1961-1984 (Box Box 2)
  - International Dendrology Society, 1974-1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
  - "I-J", 1965-1981 (Box Box 2)
  - "K", 1973-1984 (Box Box 2)
  - "L", 1973-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - "M", 1970-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Morris Arboretum, 1972-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - "N", 1974-1983 (Box Box 3)
  - National Arboretum, 1967-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - "O", 1972-1984 (Box Box 4)
  - "P", 1973-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - "R", 1970-1984 (Box Box 4)
  - Rhododendron, 1971-1984 (Box Box 4)
  - Royal Horticultural Society, 1972-1984 (Box Box 5)
  - "S", 1966-1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - "T", 1971-1983 (Box Box 5)
  - "V", 1974-1982 (Box Box 5)
  - "W", 1973-1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - "Y-Z", 1973-1978 (Box Box 5)
- Series II: Topical
  - American Horticultural Society, 1974-1975 (Box Box 6)
  - Articles by Henry T. Skinner, 1937-1979, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Awards of Henry T. Skinner, 1961-1980 (Box Box 6)
  - Azalea Handbook, 1951-1981 (Box Box 6)
  - Biographical Sketches, 1973-1983 (Box Box 6)
  - Birds and Plants, 1971 (Box Box 6)
  - Bonsai, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Champion Tree Registry of Henderson County Committee, 1978-1980 (Box Box 6)
  - Chrysanthemums, n.d. (Box Box 6)
  - Dissertation of Dr. Skinner (extra copies), 1952 (Box Box 6)
  - Feasibility Study for a Tropical Botanical Garden in Hawaii, 1963-1968 (Box Box 6)
  - Liriope, etc., 1965-1972 (Box Box 6)
  - Nantahala National Forest, 1976-1979, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 6)
  - Native Azaleas, 1935-1979; (2 folders) (Box Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1941-1971, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Plant Culture, 1979-1982 (Box Box 7)
  - Plant Hardiness Map, 1965-1977 (Box Box 7)
  - Printed Material, 1930-1976, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 7)
  - Publicity Newsclippings & Photographs, 1960-1977, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Rhododendrons, 1960-1976, n.d. (Box Box 7)
  - Rhododendron and Azalea Varieties, 1983 & n.d. (Box Box 8)
  - Rhododendron japonicum, 1983 (Box Box 8)
  - Rhododendron Quarterly Bulletin, 1975-1983 (Box Box 8)
  - Rhododendron Registration, 1971-1981 (Box Box 8)
  - Rhododendron Seed Exchange, 1976-1984 (Box Box 8)
  - Rhododendron Species Foundation, 1974-1984; (2 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - Rhododendron Study Group, 1981-1984 (Box Box 8)
  - Scrapbook File, 1936-1972 (Box Box 8)
  - Seton Belt Tract, n.d. (Box Box 8)
  - Social Functions, 1964-1977, n.d. (Box Box 8)
  - "Systematics and Taxonomy of the Ericales..." A Lab Report by Henry T. Skinner, w/ notes, 1951 (Box Box 9)
  - Talks, 1931-1984, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 9)
  - Time-Life Books Consultant, 1979 (Box Box 9)
  - Winterthur Gardens & Grounds Advisory Committee, 1975-1984 (Box Box 9)
  - Winterthur Museum, 1978 (Box Box 9)
- Series III: Bound Volumes
  - Record of Rhododendron Crosses (Partial), 1935-1972 (Box Box 10)
  - Thesis of Dr. Skinner entitled "Experiments in the Propagation of Rhododendrons and Other Ericaceous Plants by Cutting", 1938 (Box Box 10)
  - Rhododendron & Azalea Notes, 1947-1948 (Box Box 10)
  - Southern Collecting Trip Record Book, 1951; (2 volumes) (Box Box 10)
  - Southern Collecting Trip Expense Book, 1951 (Box Box 10)
  - Notes of Southern Collecting Trip Routes, 1951 (Box Box 10)
  - Dissertation of Dr. Skinner entitled Character Patterns in the Early Flowering Azaleas of the Southern U.S., 1952 (Box Box 10)